Railroad Industrial Relations Project Oral History Interviews Audiorecordings 5481 AV
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Railroad Industrial Relations Project Oral History Interviews Audiorecordings
1973
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Freilicher, Miriam
Morris, James O.
5481 AV
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Interviews.
Open reel audio tapes of oral history interviews conducted by Miriam Freilicher and James O. Morris. Transcripts are located in collection 6058, box 13.
5653567
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, December 01, 2017
EAD encoding:
Elizabeth Parker, December 01, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Railroad Industrial Relations Project [RIRP] was established on July 1, 1969 in an agreement between the United Transportation Union [UTU] and the School of Industrial and Labor Relations [ILR], Cornell University. The purpose of the project was to document the formation of the UTU and the history of its predecessor brotherhoods. In addition to collecting the records of the UTU and its predecessor organizations, the RIRP conducted numerous oral histories with local and national officers of the UTU and its predecessor organizations. These interviews were collected between 1970 and 1971 in an effort to document the unification effort, the effect it had on members of the predecessor brotherhoods, and the everyday lives of railroad employees (these interviews may be located in Collection 6058).
To supplement this collection of oral histories, the RIRP decided to conduct additional oral histories with representatives of the railroad carriers in 1973. The RIRP reached out to the National Railway Labor Conference [NRLC] to arrange for this. The NRLC is the industrywide bargaining agent for the railroads. It was formed in 1962 with the merger of the regional Carriers' Conference Committees (Western, Eastern, and Southeastern) so that there would be one entity with which to negotiate. The RIRP interviewed three executives of the NRLC (Hiltz, Dempsey, Parks) to document management's perspective on the industry and labor relations.
The RIRP also reached out to a former president of the industry trade group, the Association of American Railroads (loomis), and the vice president of personnel for the Illinois Central Gulf Railroad (Oliver) to further broaden the documentation of management's perspective.
Three additional interviews with two UTU officers were also conducted in 1973, and they are included in this collection. The interview with H.E. Gilbert and his wife, Alice, and the interview of James Paddock by Miriam Freilicher provide biographical information about these two labor leaders. The second interview with Mr. Paddock focuses on alcoholism, substance abuse, and the ways in which these diseases may be fought within the railroad industry.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1973
Bulk dates: 1973
This collection consists of the open reel audio tapes of oral history interviews conducted by Miriam Feilicher, assistant archivist for the Railroad Industrial Relations Project, and James O. Morris, professor at the New York State School of Labor and Industrial Relations.
The oral histories were conducted as part of the Railroad Industrial Relations Project. The majority of these interviews forcus on management's perspective on the railroad industry: five of the interviewees are from management; two are labor representatives.
The interviews were conducted with:
1. J.P. Hiltz, former chairman of the National Railway Labor Conference (3 tapes)
2. Daniel P. Loomis, retired president of the Association of American Railroads (1 tape)
3. James A. Paddock, retired president of the Order of Railway Conductors [interviewed twice] (3 tapes)
4. Earl Oliver, vice-president for personnel, Illinois Central Gulf Railroad (1 tape)
5. H.E. Gilbert, retired president of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, and Mrs. Alice Gilbert
6. William H. Dempsey, chairman of the National Railway Labor Conference (1 tape)
7. Maynard E. Parks, vice-chairman of the National Railway Labor Conference (1 tape)
The transcripts of these interviews may be found in Collection 6058, Box 13.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4073: James O. Morris Office Files 5148: Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen Records 5833: James A. Paddock Additional Papers 5295: Illinois Central Gulf Railroad Company Selected Personnel Files 5188 AV: Association of American Railroads "Railroad Regulation: An Absurd Game" Slide Transparencies and Sound Recording 5188m: Association of American Railroads Agreement of May 1936 5141: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Records 5205: National Railway Labor Conference Additional Records 5205 mf: National Railway Labor Conference Records on Microfilm 5329: National Railway Labor Conference Circulars 6058 OH: Kheel Center Collection of Oral Histories
Freilicher, Miriam; Morris, James Oliver, 1923-; Dempsey, William H.; Gilbert, H. E.; Hiltz, J. P.; Loomis, Daniel P.; Oliver, Earl; Paddock, James A.; Parks, Maynard E.; National Railway Labor Conference; Association of American Railroads; Order of Railway Conductors; Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; Illinois Central Gulf Railroad
5653567
- Hiltz, J. P. [tape 1 of 3], 1973; 1 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  6058 OH, Box 13, Folders 12 and 13. Born September 8, 1911 in Baltimore, Maryland. Interview provides a biography of Hiltz's life. Former Chairman of the National Railway Labor Conference. Interviewed by James O. Morris.
- Hiltz, J. P. [tape 2 of 3], 1973; 2 (Box 1)
  6058 OH, Box 13, Folders 12 and 13 Born September 8, 1911 in Baltimore, Maryland Interview provides a biography of Hiltz's life Former Chairman of the National Railway Labor Conference Interviewed by James O. Morris
- Hiltz, J. P. [tape 3 of 3], 1973; 3 (Box 1)
- Loomis, Daniel P., 1973; 4 (Box 1)
  6058 OH, Box 13, Folder 2 Born April 6, 1973 in Burlington, Vermont Interview provides a biography of Loomis' life Retired President of the Association of American Railroads Interviewed by Professor James Morris on August 1, 1973
- Paddock, James A. (interviewed by M. Freilicher) [tape 1 of 2], 1973; 5 (Box 1)
  Transcript in 6058 OH, Box 13, Folder 6 Born April 1, 1916 in Garfield, Utah Interview provides a biography of Paddock's life Retired President of the Order of Railway Conductors Interviewed by Miriam S. Freilicher on June 28, 1973 around 2:00 p.m.
- Paddock, James A. (interviewed by M. Freilicher) [tape 2 of 2], 1973; 6 (Box 1)
- Paddock, James A. (interviewed by J. Morris), 1973; 7 (Box 1)
  6058 OH, Box 13, Folder 4 Born April 1, 1916 in Garfield, Utah Retired President of the Order of Railway Conductors Interview about alcoholism and how it affected his personal life He is retired and a consultant on alcohol and drug abuse programs in the country Interviewed by James O. Morris, Cornell ILR Professor
- Oliver, Earl, 1973; 8 (Box 1)
  6058 OH, Box 13, Folder 11 Born in 1917 in Montecello, Kentucky Interviewed about his life and his work in the railroad industry Vice President for Personnel of the Illinois Central Gulf Railroad Interviewed by James O. Morris
- Gilbert, H.E., Mr. and Mrs. (Interviewed by J. Morris), 1973; 9 (Box 1)
  6058 OH, Box 13, Folder 10 Interview explores his personal and family experiences Retired president of Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Interviewed by James O. Morris on May 29, 1973 in Sun City, Arizona
- Dempsey, William H. (Interviewed by M. Freilicher), 1973; 10 (Box 1)
  6058 OH, Box 13, Folder 9 Born December 1, 1930 in New Ulm, Minnesota Interviewed about his life and work in the Railroad Industry Chairman, National Railway Labor Conference Interviewed by Miriam Freilicher on April 13, 1973
- Parks, M.E. (Interviewed by M. Freilicher), 1973; 11 (Box 1)
  6058 OH, Box: 13, Folder 14: Born May 29th, 1913 in Seattle, Washington Interviewed about her life and work in the Railroad Industry Vice Chairman of the National Railway Labor Conference Interviewed by Miriam Freilicher